Social Welfare, School of; Records ua690
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
School of Social Welfare Records
1964-2000
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
School of Social Welfare
ua690
23.4 cubic ft.
The School of Social Welfare Records document the history and day-to-day operations of the School at the University at Albany since its first full year of operation in 1964 through 2000.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Web Archives
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted with the exception of the folders marked on the inventory below.
Acquisition Information
The School of Social Welfare transferred 3 cubic feet of materials to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in the late 1980s and the remainder in 2000.
Administrative History
The Board of Trustees of the State University of New York established the School of Social Welfare in December of 1963. Impetus for creation of the School came as a result of two reports, the Moreland Commission Report in January of 1963 and the New York State Committee Report on Medical Education in June of 1963. Both reports concluded that the State of New York faced critical shortage of social workers. As one means of alleviating this shortage, a new School of Social Welfare was proposed situated on the campus of the State University of New York at Albany (SUNYA).
In 1964, Dr. Richardson L. Rice was appointed the school's first dean and began efforts to establish a two-year master's program in social welfare. The first class of twenty-seven students entered the master's program in the fall of 1965 and graduated on June 11, 1967. The Council of Social Work Education (CSWE) granted accreditation for the master's program in 1969.
1968 saw the founding of the associated Institute of Gerontology. The study of aging would later develop into a major research and teaching emphasis of the School of Social Welfare. From 1981 to 1997, in recognition of the support received from Rhoda and Stan Ringel, the Institute was called the Ringel Institute of Gerontology.
In 1970, the University Senate approved the bachelor's degree program in Social Welfare and initial consideration was given to a proposal for a Ph. D. program. The undergraduate course offerings began in the 1970-1971 school year, and the Schools' master's program was reaccredited. A broadening of the curriculum also occurred with the addition of required courses in geriatrics, social policy analysis, and program development. Social policy analysis became a formal area of concentration and the School added a new concentration in Social Welfare Administration to the curriculum.
The early 1970s saw a rising chorus of demands for SUNYA to become active in working for social change. The School of Social Welfare responded to this demand by continuing its pursuit of minority students and faculty, and creating a number of programs that focused on social problems. A Social Service Study Unit was created to refer student volunteers to local agencies. A Neighborhood Services Unit (renamed the Neighborhood Outreach Unit in 1973) was also created to provide assistance to inner city residents. Stationed in Arbor Hill, this unit functioned as a clinical teaching facility, providing counseling to married couples and aid to senior citizens. Together these two programs constituted the Community Service Program, designed to involve enrolled students in volunteer social work.
Despite the decline in federal support and the precarious nature of state finances during the early 1970s, the School launched a number of new initiatives. In the fall of 1972, a full undergraduate major was offered leading to a B.S. degree. By the spring of 1973 the undergraduate degree program was accredited. The School introduced field instruction in 1973-1974 with courses offered in state and private agencies where staff and personnel supervised and instructed enrolled students. The 1972-1973 school year saw the newly created Institute of Gerontology collaborate with the State Office for the Aging in research projects.
In the face of continued fiscal strain, the School launched new programs in continuing education during 1974-1975. These included an extended study management program and a comprehensive education program for child welfare workers. Both concentrated on problems associated with child abuse and were designed to allow part-time study toward a professional degree. By 1976 these programs enrolled 750 county and state agency personnel. The relationships established between the School and outside community agencies and institutions helped the School obtain $1.3 million dollars in grants.
The State of New York, as well as the various regional agencies, sought to use the School's expertise to solve pressing social problems. In 1976, the State requested services to aid with the Temporary State Commission on Child Welfare. The State wanted to develop a new legal service manual for child welfare workers, overhaul state laws concerning child welfare and institute new training programs for social workers. The School contributed to these goals by creating the Continuing Education Project, later renamed the Continuing Education Program (CEP), during 1975-1976 to extend educational opportunities to state and local social service agencies and by sponsoring numerous educational conferences.
The creation of the Nelson A. Rockefeller College of Public Affairs and Policy in 1981-1982 and the incorporation of the School of Social Welfare into the College signaled renewed growth for the School. The first evidence of this development was the establishment of an accelerated bachelor's/master's degree program offering a shortened program (12 months instead of 18). The school also implemented program changes to meet the needs of part-time students. The SUNY Board of Trustees approved the long-planned Ph. D. in Social Welfare in 1982, and the program accepted its first doctoral candidates in 1984.
The creation of Rockefeller College provided impetus for the School of Social Welfare to pool its resources with other schools in the College. By the mid-1980s the School cooperated in a number of endeavors with the Schools of Criminal Justice, Public Administration, and Public Policy. Plans were also made to create a graduate program incorporating Health Policy and Management.
Currently, the School of Social Welfare offers bachelor's, master's and doctoral degrees with B.S.W. and M.S.W. programs accredited by the Council on Social Work Education, the national accrediting body. There continues to be a strong emphasis on community engagement at the local level, and research and field work opportunities are now global in scope with international programs in Ireland, South Africa, South Korea, Russia, Peru, and other countries.
In line with community engagement, the School maintains a commitment to investigation of the evolving human needs of the 21st century. To achieve this goal the School offers a broad spectrum of research opportunities through various research centers and institutes, including the Center for Excellence in Aging Services and Community Wellness, the Center for Human Services Research, the Center for Innovation in Mental Health Research, the Institute of Gerontology, the National Child Welfare Workforce Institute, and the New York State Social Work Education Consortium.
Deans of the School of Social Welfare
1964-1969 Richardson L. Rice
1969-1970 Charles T. O'Reilly
1970-1971 William S. Rooney, Acting Dean
1971-1976 Charles T. O'Reilly
1976-1980 Seth W. Spellman
1980-1989 Stuart Kirk
1989-1990 Susan R. Sherman, Acting Dean
1990-2000 Lynn Videcka-Sherman
2000-present Katharine Briar-Lawson
Scope and Contents
The records of the School of Social Welfare span from the School's first full year of operation in 1964 to 2000. Early records relating to the founding of the School include annual reports from 1967-1968 through 1977-1978, accreditation reports and internal self-studies from 1966-1975, proposals for the bachelor's, master's, and the Ph. D. programs, faculty meeting minutes from 1965-1971, and various School of Social Welfare bulletins from the 1960s and 1970s. The bulk of the materials, however, document the day-to-day operations of the School from 1990-2000, during Lynn Videcka-Sherman's tenure as dean. There is little correspondence or other communication from deans prior to Videcka-Sherman. A significant portion of the records consist of publications from the Resource Guide Series produced by the Continuing Education Program, ranging from 1973-1990.
Related collections include Maureen C. Diedier, School of Social Welfare 25th Anniversary Oral History Collection (UA-902.019) and the Ringel Institute for Gerontology Records (UA–690.015).
Photographs of faculty and students from the School of Social Welfare from the University Archives Photograph Collection are available for viewing online from the University at Albany Libraries' Digital Collections database.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
All series are arranged chronologically with the exception of Series 5 and Series 6, which are arranged alphabetically.
Social Activists and Public Advocates; Senior Citizens; Albany, New York; Resource guide series (State University of New York at Albany. School of Social Welfare. Continuing Education Program); Schools of social work--United States; Schools of social work--Faculty; Social service--Vocational guidance--United States; Social service--Accreditation--United States; Community-based social services--United States; Schools of social work--Entrance requirements; Schools of social work--Admission; Social service--Fieldwork--Study and teaching--United States.; Social service--New York (State); Albany (N.Y.); Budgets; Bulletins; Administrative records; Minutes (administrative records); Agendas (administrative records); Newsletters; Publications; Correspondence; Clippings; Annual reports; Files by subject; Web Archives; UAlbany Schools & Colleges; State University of New York at Albany; State University of New York at Albany. School of Social Welfare; National Association of Deans and Directors of Schools of Social Work (U.S.); Rockefeller College of Public Affairs and Policy; Council on Social Work Education.; State University of New York at Albany. School of Social Welfare. Continuing Education Program; State University of New York at Albany. School of Social Welfare. Continuing Education Project
- Office of the Dean, 1984-1999; Undated; 1; 3 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Most materials from this series relate to the period from 1990-2000, during which time Lynn Videcka-Sherman was dean of the School of Social Welfare. These materials represent the day-to-day files from the dean’s office, and include correspondence and other communication throughout the series. There is a sizeable amount of materials relating to the National Association of Deans and Directors of Social Work (NADD), including agendas and planning documents for annual meetings. Lynn Videcka-Sherman acted as president of NADD from 1993-1995 and the materials reflect her time with the organization. Other associations represented include the New York State Association of Deans of Social Work Schools and the New York Chapter of the National Association of Social Work.
  In 1997 a shift in record keeping occurred with a new system of filing all communications and day-to-day documents in folders labeled generically as "day file." This shift differed from the previous method of filing dean's correspondence and memoranda in separate folders for each year and of creating more specific folders for other materials. The archivist elected to maintain original order of the materials.
  - National Conference of Deans and Directors Implementation Task Force, 1984-1987 (Box 1 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 1-2)
  - New York State Association of Deans of Social Work Schools, 1988-1989; Undated (Box 1 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 3)
  - NADD Meetings, 1988-1990; Undated (Box 1 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 4-5)
  - 1989 Dean's Correspondence - [RESTRICTED], 1989-1990 (Box 1 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 6-8)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Must consult archivist before viewing this material.
  - 1993 Dean's Memoranda - [RESTRICTED], 1989-1993 (Box 1 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 9-11)
  - 1990 Dean's Memoranda (Box 1 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 12-13)
  - 1990 Dean's Correspondence - [RESTRICTED], Undated (Box 1 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 14-15)
  - NADD Public Health Service Act, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 16)
  - New York State Association of Deans of Social Work Schools, 1990; Undated (Box 1 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 17)
  - NADD March 1991 Meeting - New Orleans, 1990-1991 (Box 1 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 18)
  - NADD Publications, 1990-1991 (Box 1 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 19)
  - NADD Deanship Study Committee Correspondence and Planning - Social Work Deanship Book, 1990-1993 (Box 1 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 20)
  - NADD January 1995 Retreat - Washington, 1990; 1994-1995; Undated (Box 1 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 21)
  - 1991 Dean's Correspondence (Box 1 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 22-23)
  - 1991 Dean's Memoranda (Box 1 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 24)
  - NADD October 1991 Meeting - Key West (Box 1 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 25)
  - New York State Association of Deans of Social Work Schools, 1991; Undated (Box 1 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 26-27)
  - NADD Information Committee, 1991-1992; Undated (Box 1 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 28)
  - NADD October 1992 Meeting - Santa Fe, 1991-1994; Undated (Box 1 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 29)
  - 1994 Dean's Memoranda - [RESTRICTED], 1991 (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 1-2)
  - 1993-1994 NADD President's Correspondence, 1991-1996; Undated (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 3)
  - 1992 Dean's Correspondence - [RESTRICTED] (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 4)
  - NADD Publications, 1992 (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 5)
  - NADD Reports, 1992 (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 6)
  - NADD March 1992 Meeting - Kansas City, Undated (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 7)
  - New York State Association of Deans of Social Work Schools, 1992; Undated (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 8)
  - NADD Deanship Survey, 1992-1993; 1995; Undated (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 9)
  - 1993 Dean's Correspondence (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 10-12)
  - NADD National Institute of Mental Health, 1993 (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 13)
  - NADD Study of the Deanship Dataset Request, 1993 (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 14)
  - Millennium Project, 1993; Undated (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 15)
  - NADD Business Meeting February 1993 - New York, Undated (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 16)
  - NADD October 1993 Meeting - Puerto Rico, Undated (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 17)
  - NADD October 1993 - Puerto Rico Barbara Blum Speech (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 18)
  - New York State Association of Deans of Social Work Schools, 1993; Undated (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 19-20)
  - 1994 Dean's Correspondence - [RESTRICTED] (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 21-22)
  - NADD Female Deans, 1994 (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 23)
  - NADD Study - Social Work Deans in the 1990s: Survey Findings, 1994 (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 24)
  - NADD March 1994 Meeting - Atlanta, Undated (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 25)
  - NADD October 1994 Meeting - Myrtle Beach, Undated (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 26)
  - New York State Association of Deans of Social Work Schools, 1994 (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 27-28)
  - 1995 Dean's Correspondence - [RESTRICTED] (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 29-30)
  - 1995 Dean's Memoranda (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 31)
  - NADD Legislative Affairs, 1995 (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 32)
  - NADD March 1995 Meeting - San Diego (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 33)
  - 1995-1997 NADD Program Committee (Box 2 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 34)
  - New York State Association of Deans of Social Work Schools, 1995 (Box 3 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 1)
  - NADD Fall 1995 Meeting - San Antonio (Box 3 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 2)
  - NADD Organizational Priorities Committee, 1995; Undated (Box 3 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 3)
  - NADD Newsletter, 1995-1996 (Box 3 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 4)
  - 1996 Dean's Correspondence - [RESTRICTED] (Box 3 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 5)
  - Fall 1996 Correspondence - [RESTRICTED] (Box 3 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 6)
  - Fall 1996 Memoranda - [RESTRICTED] (Box 3 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 7)
  - 1996 NADD Meetings, Undated (Box 3 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 8)
  - New York State Association of Deans of Social Work Schools, 1996-1997 (Box 3 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 9-10)
  - 1997 Dean's Correspondence - [RESTRICTED] (1 - 2 of 4 folders) (Box 3 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 11-12)
  - 1997 Dean's Correspondence - [RESTRICTED] (3 - 4 of 4 folders) (Box 4 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 1-2)
  - 1997 Dean's Memoranda (Box 4 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 3)
  - Day File - [RESTRICTED] (1 - 6 of 7 folders), 1997-1999; Undated (Box 4 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 4-9)
  - Day File - [RESTRICTED] (7 of 7 folders), 1997-1999; Undated (Box 5 (1-Office of the Dean), Folder 1)
- Administrative, 1965-2000; Undated; 2; 0.7 cubic ft.
  The majority of the Administrative series includes annual reports for the School of Social Welfare and the Continuing Education Program, and a variety of budgetary reports for programs within the School of Social Welfare. Correspondence and memoranda relating to administrative and budgetary issues are also included, with a large portion relating to the executive order for a hiring freeze by Governor George Pataki in January 1995 in response to the 1995-1996 New York State budget deficit. These documents and communication outline contingency plans and scenarios for budget cuts and the affect those cuts would have on the School of Social Welfare.
  - 1967/1968 - 1968/1969 Annual Reports (Box 1 (2-Administrative), Folder 1)
  - Budget Request - Doctoral Program, ca. 1970 (Box 1 (2-Administrative), Folder 2)
  - 1970/1971 - 1972/1973 Annual Reports, 1971-1973 (Box 1 (2-Administrative), Folder 3)
  - 1971/1972 Annual Report Community Service Program (Box 1 (2-Administrative), Folder 4)
  - 1973/1974 - 1974/1975 Annual Reports (Box 1 (2-Administrative), Folder 5)
  - 1975/1976 Annual Report of the Continuing Education Project (Box 1 (2-Administrative), Folder 6)
  - 1975/1976 - 1976/1977 Annual Reports (Box 1 (2-Administrative), Folder 7)
  - 1977/1978 Annual Reports (Box 1 (2-Administrative), Folder 8)
  - 1994-1995 Budget Cuts - [RESTRICTED], Undated (Box 1 (2-Administrative), Folder 9-11)
  - 1994-1995 Income Reimbursable Budget, Undated (Box 1 (2-Administrative), Folder 12)
  - Budget Reduction Contingency and Planning Program Decisions, 1995-1996 (Box 1 (2-Administrative), Folder 13)
  - 1996-1997 Budget, 1995-1996; Undated (Box 2 (2-Administrative), Folder 1-2)
  - Budget Reports, 1998-2000 (Box 2 (2-Administrative), Folder 3)
  - 1998-1999 Budget, Undated (Box 2 (2-Administrative), Folder 4)
  - 1999-2000 Budget Preparation (Box 2 (2-Administrative), Folder 5)
- Accreditation, 1965-1995; Undated; 3; 2.2 cubic ft.
  The Accreditation series is composed primarily of reports created by the School of Social Welfare for use in the accreditation and reaccreditation processes. These reports include information on courses, faculty member curriculum vitae, data about the school, and self-study reports. Also included in the series are correspondence, memoranda, and other communications primarily directed to and from the current dean relating to the school’s accreditation process. Other materials include accreditation manuals and guidelines from the accrediting body, the Council on Social Work Education (CSWE).
  - 1982 Accreditation Site Team Visit, 1965-1982 (Box 1 (3-Accreditation), Folder 1)
  - Accreditation Study Vol. I - Self Study, 1966 (Box 1 (3-Accreditation), Folder 2)
  - Accreditation Study Vol. 2 - Illustrative Material, 1966 (Box 1 (3-Accreditation), Folder 3-6)
  - 1967 On-Campus Visit for Accreditation (Box 1 (3-Accreditation), Folder 7)
  - Accreditation Study Vol. I - Self Study, 1969 (Box 1 (3-Accreditation), Folder 8)
  - Accreditation Study Vol. I - A Self Study Faculty Vitae, 1969 (Box 1 (3-Accreditation), Folder 9)
  - Accreditation Study Vol. II - Self Study, 1969 (Box 1 (3-Accreditation), Folder 10)
  - 1976 Reaccreditation of M.S.W. Program, 1969; 1975-1979; Undated (Box 1 (3-Accreditation), Folder 11)
  - Manual of Accrediting Standards, 1971 (Box 1 (3-Accreditation), Folder 12)
  - Mandatory Review Following Accreditation, 1972 (Box 1 (3-Accreditation), Folder 13)
  - Accrediting Standards and Guidelines for Non-Discrimination, 1973; 1976-1977; Undated (Box 1 (3-Accreditation), Folder 14)
  - Application for Approval: Undergraduate Social Work Program - CSWE, 1973 (Box 1 (3-Accreditation), Folder 15)
  - HEW Regulations on Protection of Human Subjects, 1973 (Box 1 (3-Accreditation), Folder 16)
  - Internal Evaluation Report, 1973 (Box 1 (3-Accreditation), Folder 17)
  - Status Report and Projections for the School of Social Welfare, 1973 (Box 1 (3-Accreditation), Folder 18)
  - Application for Accreditation: CSWE, 1974 (Box 1 (3-Accreditation), Folder 19)
  - Application for Accreditation: CSWE - Appendix, 1974 (Box 1 (3-Accreditation), Folder 20-21)
  - 1975 Accreditation, 1974-1975 (Box 1 (3-Accreditation), Folder 22-23)
  - Accreditation Study Vol. I (1 of 2 folders), 1975 (Box 1 (3-Accreditation), Folder 24)
  - Accreditation Study Vol. I (2 of 2 folders), 1975 (Box 2 (3-Accreditation), Folder 1)
  - Reaccreditation Study Vol. II - Self Study Part A, 1975 (Box 2 (3-Accreditation), Folder 2-4)
  - Reaccreditation Study Vol. II - Self Study Part B, 1975 (Box 2 (3-Accreditation), Folder 5-6)
  - 1977 Reaccreditation, 1977-1978 (Box 2 (3-Accreditation), Folder 7)
  - Consultant's Report for Reaccreditation (Betty Bauer, May 1979) (Box 2 (3-Accreditation), Folder 8)
  - Accreditation 1982: Self Study Outline, 1981 (Box 2 (3-Accreditation), Folder 9)
  - Accreditation 1982: Subcommittee List, 1981 (Box 2 (3-Accreditation), Folder 10)
  - 1982 Accreditation: Site Team Report, 1981-1982; Undated (Box 2 (3-Accreditation), Folder 11)
  - 1982 Accreditation: SSW Response to Site Team Report, 1981-1982; Undated (Box 2 (3-Accreditation), Folder 12-14)
  - Reaccreditation Congratulations, 1982 (Box 2 (3-Accreditation), Folder 15)
  - Accreditation Progress Report, 1984; Undated (Box 2 (3-Accreditation), Folder 16-17)
  - Accreditation: 1987 Eligibility Documentation, 1987-1988 (Box 2 (3-Accreditation), Folder 18)
  - 1988 Reaccreditation, 1987-1989; Undated (Box 2 (3-Accreditation), Folder 19-20)
  - 1988 Commission on Accreditation Handbook of Accreditation Standards and Procedures (Box 2 (3-Accreditation), Folder 21-22)
  - Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools Reaccreditation Study, 1989-1990; Undated (Box 2 (3-Accreditation), Folder 23)
  - 1991 Commission on Accreditation Handbook of Standards and Procedures (Box 2 (3-Accreditation), Folder 24)
  - 1995 Reaccreditation Site Team Visit, 1993-1995; Undated (Box 3 (3-Accreditation), Folder 1-2)
- Faculty, 1965-1997; Undated; 4; 2.3 cubic ft.
  Arranged chronologically